<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="kr"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pelu10075.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://pelu10075.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="kr"/><updated>2025-06-11T08:23:17+00:00</updated><id>https://pelu10075.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Flu’s Logbook</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">What is Linear Algebra?</title><link href="https://pelu10075.github.io/blog/2025/What-is-Linear-Algebra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Linear Algebra?"/><published>2025-06-10T14:10:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-10T14:10:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pelu10075.github.io/blog/2025/What%20is%20Linear%20Algebra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pelu10075.github.io/blog/2025/What-is-Linear-Algebra/"><![CDATA[<p>Linear algebra is a branch of mathematics centered around <strong>vectors</strong>, <strong>matrices</strong>, and <strong>linear transformations</strong>. These theories are not confined to math textbooks—they are actively used in fields like <strong>computer science</strong>, <strong>economics</strong>, and <strong>natural sciences</strong>.</p> <p>In particular, <strong>computer science</strong> relies on linear algebra as a foundational component for core technologies such as artificial intelligence, graphics, and data analysis.</p> <p>In this blog series, I aim to <strong>explain the concepts and applications of linear algebra from a computer science perspective</strong>, in an approachable way. Even if you’re not familiar with mathematics, the posts will be structured to help you understand through real-world applications and examples.</p> <p>Since there’s some space left in this introductory post, I’ll also cover the historical background of linear algebra, its applications, and an outline of future posts.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="historical-background-of-linear-algebra">Historical Background of Linear Algebra</h2> <p>Although linear algebra is a key part of modern mathematics, its roots go back as far as 3000 BCE. The terminology of vectors and matrices is relatively modern, but the ideas themselves existed long ago.</p> <h3 id="1-ancient-babylon-3000-bce">1. Ancient Babylon (~3000 BCE)</h3> <p>The Babylonians were capable of solving systems of equations up to the third degree. While they didn’t use symbolic notation, they had algorithms equivalent to solving linear equations.</p> <ul> <li>Source: Victor J. Katz, <em>A History of Mathematics: An Introduction</em>, Addison-Wesley, 2009.</li> </ul> <h3 id="2-ancient-china--the-nine-chapters-on-the-mathematical-art-2nd-century-bce">2. Ancient China – <em>The Nine Chapters on the Mathematical Art</em> (~2nd century BCE)</h3> <p>The chapter “Fangcheng” in <em>The Nine Chapters</em> describes a method for solving systems of linear equations, similar to Gaussian elimination.</p> <ul> <li>Source: Joseph Needham, <em>Science and Civilisation in China, Volume 3</em>, Cambridge University Press, 1959.</li> </ul> <h3 id="3-18th19th-century-europe--birth-of-matrix-theory">3. 18th–19th Century Europe – Birth of Matrix Theory</h3> <p><strong>Gabriel Cramer (1750)</strong>: Introduced Cramer’s Rule for solving systems of linear equations.</p> <p><strong>Carl Friedrich Gauss (1800s)</strong>: Formalized the <strong>Gaussian elimination</strong> method.</p> <p><strong>Augustin-Louis Cauchy (1820s)</strong>: Organized the concepts of matrices and determinants.</p> <p><strong>Arthur Cayley &amp; James Sylvester (1850s)</strong>: Formalized the concept of matrices and laid the groundwork for matrix operations and eigenvalue theory.</p> <ul> <li>Source: Thomas Hawkins, <em>Emergence of the Theory of Lie Groups</em>, Springer, 2000; Karen Hunger Parshall, <em>James Joseph Sylvester: Jewish Mathematician in a Victorian World</em>, Johns Hopkins University Press, 2006.</li> </ul> <h3 id="4-development-of-modern-linear-algebra-earlymid-20th-century">4. Development of Modern Linear Algebra (Early–Mid 20th Century)</h3> <p>Mathematicians such as <strong>David Hilbert</strong> and <strong>Emmy Noether</strong> connected linear algebra with <strong>abstract algebra</strong> and <strong>functional analysis</strong>, and it became a key language in <strong>quantum mechanics</strong>.</p> <ul> <li>Source: I. M. Gelfand, <em>Lectures on Linear Algebra</em>, Dover Publications, 1989.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="why-linear-algebra-matters">Why Linear Algebra Matters</h2> <ol> <li> <p>Machine Learning / Deep Learning<br/> Neural networks use vectors and matrices to represent weights, input data, and more.</p> </li> <li> <p>Computer Graphics<br/> 3D transformations like rotation, scaling, and translation are represented using matrices.</p> </li> <li> <p>Physics<br/> In quantum mechanics, vector spaces are used to describe physical states.</p> </li> <li> <p>Statistics / Data Analysis<br/> Tools like covariance matrices and principal component analysis (PCA) rely heavily on linear algebra.</p> </li> </ol> <hr/> <h2 id="upcoming-posts">Upcoming Posts</h2> <ol> <li>Common Terminology in Linear Algebra</li> <li>Vectors and Matrices</li> <li>Linear Transformations</li> <li>Determinants</li> <li>Cross Product and Dot Product</li> <li>Eigenvalues and Eigenvectors</li> <li>Solving Systems of Linear Equations</li> <li>LU Decomposition</li> <li>Gauss–Jordan Elimination</li> <li>Eigenvalue Decomposition</li> <li>Linear Regression</li> </ol> <hr/> <p>This post focused on summarizing the overall concepts and historical background of linear algebra. Starting with the next post, we will explore each topic in more detail.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Study"/><category term="LinearAlgebra"/><category term="EN"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction to Linear Algebra]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">선형대수학이란?</title><link href="https://pelu10075.github.io/blog/2025/%EC%84%A0%ED%98%95%EB%8C%80%EC%88%98%ED%95%99%EC%9D%B4%EB%9E%80/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="선형대수학이란?"/><published>2025-06-10T14:10:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-10T14:10:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pelu10075.github.io/blog/2025/%EC%84%A0%ED%98%95%EB%8C%80%EC%88%98%ED%95%99%EC%9D%B4%EB%9E%80</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pelu10075.github.io/blog/2025/%EC%84%A0%ED%98%95%EB%8C%80%EC%88%98%ED%95%99%EC%9D%B4%EB%9E%80/"><![CDATA[<p>선형대수학은 <strong>벡터</strong>, <strong>행렬</strong>, 그리고 <strong>선형 변환</strong> 등을 중심으로 전개되는 수학의 한 분야이다. 이 이론들은 단순히 수학 교과서에 머무르지 않고, <strong>컴퓨터과학</strong>, <strong>경제학</strong>, <strong>자연과학</strong> 등 여러 분야에서 실제로 활용된다.</p> <p>특히 <strong>컴퓨터과학</strong>에서는 인공지능, 그래픽스, 데이터 분석 등 핵심 기술의 기반이 되는 수학이기도 하다.</p> <p>이 블로그 시리즈에서는 <strong>컴퓨터과학을 중심으로 선형대수학의 개념과 활용</strong>을 쉽게 풀어보고자 한다. 수학에 익숙하지 않아도, 실제 적용 사례와 함께 이해할 수 있도록 구성할 예정이다.</p> <p>그리고 아래는 블로그에 넣을게 없어서 역사적 배경과 사용처, 이후 예정된 포스트에 대해 다루도록 하겠다.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="선형대수학의-역사적-배경">선형대수학의 역사적 배경</h2> <p>선형대수학은 현대 수학의 핵심 분야 중 하나이지만, 그 뿌리는 기원전 3000년까지 거슬러 올라간다. 벡터와 행렬이라는 용어는 현대에 들어와 정립되었지만, 그 개념은 고대 바빌로니아에서 부터 존재했다.</p> <h3 id="1-고대-바빌로니아-기원전-3000년">1. 고대 바빌로니아 (~기원전 3000년)</h3> <p>바빌로니아인들은 2차에서 3차에 이르는 연립방정식을 풀 수 있었다. 문자 기호는 사용하지 않았으나, 이미 선형 방정식을 푸는 알고리즘을 알고 있었다 할 수 있다.</p> <ul> <li>출처: Victor J. Katz, <em>A History of Mathematics: An Introduction</em>, Addison-Wesley, 2009.</li> </ul> <h3 id="2-고대-중국---구장산술九章算術-기원전-2세기">2. 고대 중국 - 『구장산술(九章算術)』 (~기원전 2세기)</h3> <p>『구장산술』의 ‘방정’ 장에서는 가우스 소거법과 유사한 방식의 선형 방정식 풀이법이 소개되어 있다.</p> <ul> <li>출처: Joseph Needham, <em>Science and Civilisation in China, Volume 3</em>, Cambridge University Press, 1959.</li> </ul> <h3 id="3-1819세기-유럽--행렬-이론의-시작">3. 18–19세기 유럽 – 행렬 이론의 시작</h3> <p><strong>Gabriel Cramer (1750)</strong>: 연립방정식의 해법으로 크래머의 공식을 제시했다.</p> <p><strong>Carl Friedrich Gauss (1800s)</strong>: <strong>가우스 소거법</strong>을 정립했다.</p> <p><strong>Augustin-Louis Cauchy (1820s)</strong>: 행렬과 행렬식 개념을 정리했다.</p> <p><strong>Arthur Cayley &amp; James Sylvester (1850s)</strong>: 오늘날 우리가 아는 행렬 개념을 형식화하고, 행렬 연산과 고유값 이론의 기초를 마련했다.</p> <ul> <li>출처: Thomas Hawkins, <em>Emergence of the Theory of Lie Groups</em>, Springer, 2000., Karen Hunger Parshall, <em>James Joseph Sylvester: Jewish Mathematician in a Victorian World</em>, Johns Hopkins University Press, 2006.</li> </ul> <h3 id="4-현대-선형대수의-형성-20세기-초중반">4. 현대 선형대수의 형성 (20세기 초~중반)</h3> <p><strong>David Hilbert</strong>, <strong>Emmy Noether</strong> 등의 수학자들이 선형대수학을 <strong>추상대수학</strong>, <strong>함수해석학</strong>과 연결시키고,특히 양자역학에서 선형대수학이 필수 수학 언어로 자리잡게 되었다.</p> <ul> <li>출처: I. M. Gelfand, <em>Lectures on Linear Algebra</em>, Dover Publications, 1989.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="선형대수학이-중요한-이유">선형대수학이 중요한 이유</h2> <ol> <li> <p>기계학습 / 딥러닝</p> <p>신경망의 가중치, 입력 데이터의 표현 등 대부분의 구성 요소가 벡터와 행렬 형태로 표현된다.</p> </li> <li> <p>컴퓨터 그래픽스</p> <p>3D 회전, 확대, 이동 등을 행렬로 표현되어있다.</p> </li> <li> <p>물리학</p> <p>양자역학 등에서 상태 표현에 벡터를 사용한다.</p> </li> <li> <p>통계 / 데이터 분석</p> <p>공분산 행렬, 주성분 분석(PCA) 등 고차원 데이터 분석에서 행렬은 핵심적인 도구로 사용된다.</p> </li> </ol> <hr/> <h2 id="앞으로-다룰-포스트">앞으로 다룰 포스트</h2> <ol> <li>선형대수학에서 주로 쓰이는 용어</li> <li>벡터와 행렬</li> <li>선형 변환</li> <li>행렬식</li> <li>외적과 내적</li> <li>고윳값과 고유벡터</li> <li>선형 방정식의 해법</li> <li>LU 변환</li> <li>가우스-조던 소거법</li> <li>고윳값 분해</li> <li>선형 회귀</li> </ol> <hr/> <p>이번 글은 선형대수학의 전반적인 개념과 역사적 배경을 정리하는 데 초점을 맞췄다. 다음 글부터는 본격적으로 개별 개념들을 자세히 다루도록 하겠다.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Study"/><category term="LinearAlgebra"/><category term="KR"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[선형대수학의 서론]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">about-eng</title><link href="https://pelu10075.github.io/blog/2025/about-eng/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="about-eng"/><published>2025-06-09T23:59:59+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-09T23:59:59+00:00</updated><id>https://pelu10075.github.io/blog/2025/about-eng</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pelu10075.github.io/blog/2025/about-eng/"><![CDATA[<p>This blog was created out of a deep interest in computer programming and aims to document and share my academic journey and exploration of areas I am passionate about. Through this space, I intend to systematically organize my learning process and reflections on various STEM topics.</p> <p>The blog will primarily focus on the following subjects:</p> <p>Linear Algebra</p> <p>Calculus</p> <p>Probability and Statistics</p> <p>Graph Theory</p> <p>Algorithms</p> <p>Programming Languages</p> <p>While the blog will be written mainly in Korean, documents will be categorized by language using the tag <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">EN</code> for English posts.</p> <p>Although I am still in the process of learning, I strive to deepen my understanding of these fields through consistent study and reflection. I hope this blog becomes a meaningful space for exchanging knowledge and insights with others who share similar interests.</p> <p>Thank you.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="notice"/><category term="EN"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is the Korean translation of about.]]></summary></entry></feed>